[
  {
    "question": "What does “ignores obstacles” mean? Do Han Solo [Pilot, Customized YT-1300] and Qi’ra [Crew] work together? What about Dash Rendar [YT-2400] and Outrider [Title]?",
    "answer": "When an effect says a ship “ignores obstacles,” it means that ship “ignores the effects of obstacles.” A ship that is “ignoring obstacles” does not apply the effects of overlapping or moving through them. When that ship performs an attack that is obstructed by an obstacle it ignores the effects of the obstruction, so the defender does not roll 1 additional defense die being obstructed by the obstacles the attacker is ignoring.\n\nHowever, the obstacles are still treated as being present for effects that check for their presence or absence. Additionally, an attack is obstructed by an obstacle even while the effects of the obstacle are ignored. This applies to cards such as Outrider, Han Solo [Pilot, Customized YT-1300], and Trick Shot (Talent).\n\nAdditionally, other ships do not ignore the obstacle when resolving effects that interact with a ship that is ignoring obstacles. For instance, while a ship that is ignoring obstacles defends, if the attack is obstructed, it still rolls 1 additional defense die because the attacker is not ignoring the effects of obstacles."
  },
  {
    "question": "If the difficulty of an action is not stated (such as Lando Calrissian [Rebel, Crew]’s unique action or the coordinate action “Vizier” [TIE Reaper] can perform as part of its pilot ability), what is the difficulty of that action?",
    "answer": "White. However, note that if a ship is instructed to perform an action “on its action bar” this way, it uses the difficulty of the action on its action bar."
  },
  {
    "question": "When a ship is destroyed by a game effect triggered with \"before engaging,” does it still engage?",
    "answer": "Yes, because the game has already reached that initiative step, it is not removed until after all ships of that initiative have engaged, per simultaneous fire."
  },
  {
    "question": "Does a Proximity Mine, when dropped overlapping a ship in the System Phase, detonate immediately?",
    "answer": "Yes. When an object is placed underneath a ship, that ship counts as overlapping that object."
  },
  {
    "question": "Does the Autopilot Drone [Escape Craft]’s ability trigger if it is destroyed by another method other than running out of charges?",
    "answer": "No."
  },
  {
    "question": "Can a ship perform an attack against an enemy ship at range 0 (with bases touching) when the range from the firing arc is range 1?",
    "answer": "You cannot attack a ship at range 0 of you. This was an omission from the rules reference that will be clarified in the next update."
  },
  {
    "question": "Does Loose Cargo count as a device or obstacle, since it’s listed on the Device Rules page?",
    "answer": "It is an obstacle, not a device."
  },
  {
    "question": "When a ship moves through a Proximity Mine [Device] (and overlaps) does the timing window for Sabine Wren [Crew] occur before or after the ship has an opportunity to perform an action?",
    "answer": "Trick question! Sabine only affects devices classified as bombs, not mines and other devices, such as a Proximity Mine."
  },
  {
    "question": "If a ship with Cloaking Device [Illicit] rolls a focus result and then fails while attempting to decloak, what happens?",
    "answer": "The ship does not remove its cloak token."
  },
  {
    "question": "May a ship use Elusive [Talent] to recover charges on other upgrades by fully executing red maneuvers?",
    "answer": "No. Elusive and other effects that refer to recovering charges only apply to the charges of that specific card, unless the effect explicitly states otherwise (such as Chopper [Rebel, Crew])."
  },
  {
    "question": "If a ship performs an action and the action is modified by one or more effects that cause the ship to “treat the action as white” and one or more effects that causes the ship to “treat the action as red,” what color is the action?",
    "answer": "Red. It defaults to the more restrictive color."
  },
  {
    "question": "If a ship has red evade linked to another action (such as the TIE Aggressor or Attack Shuttle), Debris Gambit [Talent] equipped, and is within range of an obstacle, does it treat the linked red evade as white?",
    "answer": "Yes, Debris Gambit modifies any red evade action on the ship’s action bar, including linked actions."
  },
  {
    "question": "Does a ship’s firing arc extend to to range 3 even if the weapon using that arc does not?",
    "answer": "Yes. For example, if Drea Renthal (Scum, BTL-A4 Y-wing) is equipped with a Dorsal Turret [Turret], she can use her ability on ships at range 1–3 in her turret arc."
  },
  {
    "question": "Does Kavil (Scum, BTL-A4 Y-wing) roll an additional attack die when attacking with a turret weapon when the turret arc indicator is set to his front arc?",
    "answer": "Yes. Additionally, note that Kavil would roll an additional attack die when performing an attack that specifies bullseye arc, even though the target is also by definition in his front arc."
  },
  {
    "question": "If Lieutenant Sai [Lambda-class Shuttle] coordinates a ship and it performs an action followed by a linked action, can Lieutenant Sai perform the linked action instead of the initial action?",
    "answer": "No. Lieutenant Sai can only perform the initial action."
  },
  {
    "question": "Airen Cracken’s [Z-95 Headhunter] pilot ability allows another friendly ship to “perform an action, treating it as red.” Can that ship choose to perform a red action, treating it as red?",
    "answer": "Yes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Does the Wounded Pilot [Damage Card]’s first effect (“After you perform an action, roll 1 attack die. On a <hit> or <critical hit> result, gain 1 stress token.”) resolve after you repair it?",
    "answer": "No. The card is repaired, and thus has no effect to resolve."
  },
  {
    "question": "Does the StarViper-class Attack Platform’s Microthrusters ship ability affect the barrel roll that results from becoming tractored?",
    "answer": "Microthrusters does affect this barrel roll. The player whose effect assigned the tractor token determines the direction and position of the template."
  },
  {
    "question": "If the Loose Cargo from Rigged Cargo Chute [Illicit] overlaps another ship, what happens?",
    "answer": "It is placed underneath the ship, and the ship overlaps it."
  },
  {
    "question": "Do TIE Strikers (and Reapers) skip their perform action step if they overlap an asteroid or another ship with their Aileron’s ability maneuver?",
    "answer": "No. It is only during the Execute Maneuver step that a ship skips its Perform Action step for overlapping a ship or obstacle."
  },
  {
    "question": "Can an ionized ship perform an action that is linked to its focus action after performing its focus action?",
    "answer": "No. Focus is the only action that it can perform during the Perform Action step."
  },
  {
    "question": "Can a TIE Advanced x1 that rolled 1 additional die from Advanced Targeting Computer spend the lock later in the attack? If it does, can it change 1 <hit> into a <critical hit>?",
    "answer": "While performing an attack, a TIE Advanced x1 can spend its lock to reroll attack dice after rolling 1 additional die. \n\nIt can also change 1 [Hit] result to a [Critical Hit] result and then spend the lock to reroll attack dice. However, note that it cannot change 1 [Hit] result to a [Critical Hit] result after spending the lock, as it no longer has the defender locked."
  },
  {
    "question": "After being destroyed, can “Deathfire” [TIE Bomber] launch a device that cannot normally be launched?",
    "answer": "No."
  },
  {
    "question": "What ship’s initiative does Listening Device condition assigned by Informant [Crew] trigger at?",
    "answer": "Listening Device’s effect triggers at the initiative of the ship that has the condition."
  },
  {
    "question": "[Note: this is an amendment to the prior ruling from October 3rd, 2018] If a ship with Han Solo [Rebel, Gunner] is made to engage at initiative 7 (through Roark Garnet, Heightened Reflexes [Force Power], etc.), must it perform Han Solo's bonus attack first?",
    "answer": "Yes. Han Solo [Rebel, Gunner]'s effect occurs at initiative 7 before any ship at that initiative engages (including the one to which Han Solo is equipped), so Han Solo's bonus attack is always performed first. This means that it cannot perform Han Solo's bonus attack and then perform a subsequent attack from the same turret arc."
  },
  {
    "question": "How do bomb and mine devices interact with remotes?",
    "answer": "Each bomb device (Bomblet, Proton Bomb, Seismic Charge) has the following adjustment to the reference text found in the Rules Reference:\n\n-Change all instances of \"ship\" to \"ship and remote.\"\n\nMines do not affect remotes.\n\nThis will be reflected in a forthcoming update to the Rules Reference."
  },
  {
    "question": "If one effect says to \"treat an action as purple\" and another says to \"treat an action as red,\" what happens?",
    "answer": "Actions have three difficulties, from least to most restrictive: white, red, and purple.\n\nIf two or more effects would alter the color of an action from its default color, the action is treated as the most restrictive of those colors. So, if an action is \"treated as red\" and \"treated as purple\" at the same time, it is treated as purple, as this is the most restrictive."
  },
  {
    "question": "If an effect instructs a ship to gain an additional lock token (such as Petty Officer Thanisson [Crew]), can a player choose to assign the ship a lock token with a different number from the first lock token?",
    "answer": "No. It must gain a lock of the same number as the first (which, in most cases, causes the ship to lose the original lock, resulting in only one lock token)."
  },
  {
    "question": "If a Quadrijet Transfer Spacetug uses its \"Spacetug Tractor Array\" action and cannot choose a ship in its front arc at range 1, what happens?",
    "answer": "The action fails."
  },
  {
    "question": "If a ship that is equipped with Kanan Jarrus [Crew] uses Inertial Dampeners [Illicit] to perform a white stationary maneuver, in which order to Kanan's ability and the \"gain 1 stress token\" portion of Inertial Dampeners' ability occur?",
    "answer": "Both abilities have the same timing window: after the ship executes the maneuver. Thus, after the ship executes the white stationary maneuver, if the player chooses to spend one Force charge to activate Kanan, two abilities enter the ability queue: Inertial Dampeners' \"gain 1 stress token\" and Kanan Jarrus' \"remove 1 stress token.\" The player who controls both effects determines the order they enter the queue, and then the abilities resolve in that order. If a player wants the ship to gain and then remove a stress token, Inertial Dampeners' ability should be placed into the queue before Kanan's ability."
  },
  {
    "question": "Dalan Oberos [M12-L Kimogila]'s pilot ability reads \"At the start of the Engagement Phase, you may choose 1 shielded enemy ship in your bullseye arc and spend 1 charge. If you do, that ship loses 1 shield and you recover 1 shield.\" Must both \"that ship loses 1 shield\" and \"you recover 1 shield\" be able to resolve for either to resolve?",
    "answer": "Yes. \"That ship loses 1 shield and you recover 1 shield\" is a single effect, and so both parts must be able to resolve for either to occur."
  },
  {
    "question": "Do Paige Tico [Crew] and \"Deathfire\" [TIE Bomber]'s abilities supersede the \"one device per round\" limitation?",
    "answer": "Yes. These abilities allow one ship to drop a second device in the same round (at the relevant timing windows), as they do not include the \"if you have not dropped or launched a device this round\" limitation (as included on Elon Kappehl)."
  },
  {
    "question": "While a ship executes a Tallon Roll maneuver, if it cannot be placed at the middle position (center line aligned to the center line of the template), is it able to fully execute the maneuver?",
    "answer": "Yes, provided there is a valid position at which to place it. While executing a Tallon Roll, if a ship can be placed in at least one of the three possible positions (center line aligned to the front, middle, or back of the template), it must choose one of the valid positions, and it fully executes the maneuver. If a valid position exists, it cannot choose an invalid position to partially complete the maneuver. As with a barrel roll, while resolving this, the player may attempt to place the ship at the front, middle, and back before choosing a valid position."
  },
  {
    "question": "If an effect says that a ship \"loses a shield\" (or \"loses shields\"), has that ship suffered damage?",
    "answer": "No. While suffering damage does cause a ship to lose shields (if applicable), if an effect causes a ship to lose one or more shields directly, it has not suffered damage."
  },
  {
    "question": "How is Han Solo [Rebel, Modified YT-1300]'s ability categorized? Is it a dice modification? Is it a reroll? What is its timing window?",
    "answer": "Han Solo's ability is treated as a dice modification effect that is not a reroll. Because it is a dice modification effect, when attacking or defending, it triggers during the Modify Dice step. Note, however, that it can also affect other die rolls, such as the roll to determine if a ship suffers damage from overlapping or moving through an asteroid."
  },
  {
    "question": "How does Han Solo [Rebel, Modified YT-1300]'s ability interact with C-3PO [Rebel, Crew]?",
    "answer": "The \"if you do and you roll exactly that many evade results...\" portion of C-3PO's ability triggers occurs after the dice are rolled, before the Modify Dice step. Thus, Han Solo's effect occurs after C-3PO's effect has been resolved. If using Han Solo after using C-3PO, the added die must be rerolled."
  },
  {
    "question": "How does Han Solo [Rebel, Modified YT-1300]'s ability interact with \"Midnight\" [TIE/fo Fighter]?",
    "answer": "\"Midnight\" prevents dice modification. Because Han Solo's ability is a dice modification effect, \"Midnight\" prevents it from being used."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which effects are abilities?",
    "answer": "An ability is text from a card a player controls (such a ship card, upgrade card, damage card, remote card, device, condition card, etc).\n\nA few abilities are constant (such as the \"Gain a [Frontarc] primary weapon with a value of '3'\" portion of Moldy Crow). Constant abilities are not resolved via the ability queue. \n\nMost abilities are triggered, occurring only at a specified timing window (such as the \"During the End Phase, do not remove up to 2 focus tokens\" portion of Moldy Crow). Triggered abilities are resolved via the ability queue.\n\nEach triggered ability has the following parts:\n\nA timing (when the ability is added to the ability queue)\nAn effect (what the ability does)\n\nAdditionally, an ability can have one or more of the following:\n\nOne or more requirements the ship must meet\nOne or more costs the ship must pay\n\nA text box can contain multiple abilities if there are multiple constant abilities or triggers that can add an ability to the queue (as in the Moldy Crow example)."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by a \"requirement\" for an ability?",
    "answer": "A requirement for an ability is a conditional if-statement, such as \"if you are tractored\" or \"if the defender is in your bullseye arc.\" A ship being in-arc at range for an attack made as part of a triggered ability, such as Snap Shot or Foresight, is also a requirement for that ability.\n\nIf an ability's requirements are not met at the time the ability would be added to the queue, it cannot be added to the queue.\n\nIf the ability's requirements are not met at the time the ability would be resolved from the queue, the ability is not resolved and is instead removed from the queue. \n\nIf an ability instructs you to make a choice, such as choosing a ship, that is not itself a requirement to initiate an ability."
  },
  {
    "question": "When is the cost for an ability paid?",
    "answer": "The cost for an ability is paid when the ability is resolved.\n\nAn ability cannot be added to the queue if its cost could not be paid at the time it is added.\n\nIf an ability's cost cannot be paid when it would be resolved from the queue, the ability is not resolved and is instead removed from the queue. The ability's cost is not paid.\n\nAn ability can have multiple costs. If it does, all costs must be paid to resolve it. If all costs cannot be paid, no costs are paid and the ability is removed from the queue and not resolved."
  },
  {
    "question": "When specifically during an attack do effects that apply \"while you perform an attack\" or \"while you defend\" apply?",
    "answer": "Abilities are applied at the step in the attack at which they take effect. For example, in the case of Predator, as this is a dice modification, it is applied at Step 2b: Modify Attack Dice. Note, however, that effects resolved during Step 2b: Modify Attack Dice and 3b: Modify Defense Dice do not use the ability queue, as they are resolved in the order described in that section of the rules reference."
  },
  {
    "question": "If a ship executes a stationary maneuver in arc at range 2 of an enemy ship with Snap Shot equipped (or in the bullseye arc of an enemy ship with Foresight equipped), can the ship with Snap Shot (or Foresight) perform the bonus attack?",
    "answer": "Yes."
  },
  {
    "question": "While \"Scourge\" Skutu performs an attack using Snap Shot, if the defender is in \"Scourge\" Skutu's bullseye arc, does \"Scourge\" Skutu add an additional attack die?",
    "answer": "Yes."
  },
  {
    "question": "If a ship with Fine-Tuned Controls (or another ability that triggers \"after you execute/fully execute a maneuver\") fully executes a maneuver in arc at range 2 of a ship equipped with Snap Shot, how is this resolved?",
    "answer": "This is resolved one of several ways depending on which player is first player.\n\nIn all cases, both abilities (\"After you fully execute a maneuver, you may spend 1 force charge to perform a boost or barrel roll action\" and \"After an enemy ship executes a maneuver, you may perform this attack against it as a bonus attack\") are added to the ability queue.\n\nIf the first player controls the ship with Fine-Tune Controls, that player resolves this ability before Snap Shot is resolved. If, after performing a boost or barrel roll, the ship with Fine-Tuned Controls is no longer in range or arc to be chosen as a target for Snap Shot, Snap Shot cannot be resolved and is removed from the queue.\n\nIf the second player controls the ship with Fine-Tuned Controls, their opponent resolves Snap Shot first."
  },
  {
    "question": "How do abilities that alter the speed, difficulty, and/or bearing of a maneuver that a ship reveals during its Reveal Dial step and executes during its Execute Maneuver step resolve? For example, if Hera Syndulla [Attack Shuttle] is equipped with R4 Astromech and Seasoned Navigator, and also has the Damaged Engine Damage Card, what happens?",
    "answer": "R4 Astromech and Damaged Engine (and other constant effects that alter the difficulty of a maneuver, such as Nien Nunb [Crew], L3-37's Programming, and Leia Organa [Rebel and Resistance, Crew]) apply only during the Execute Maneuver step and for effects that trigger after that ship executes a maneuver.\n\nSo, after Hera's dial is revealed, Hera's player may add Hera's pilot ability and Seasoned Navigator's ability to the ability queue in either order. Both abilities resolve, and if Seasoned Navigator's ability is resolved, the difficulty of the maneuver is increased during the Execute Maneuver step (i.e. the difficulty has not yet been increased when Hera's pilot ability is resolved).\n\nThen, during the Execute Maneuver step, all abilities that alter the difficulty of the maneuver are cumulative as normal.\n\nNote that abilities that alter a maneuver without causing the ship to select a new maneuver on its dial do not affect the ship's \"revealed maneuver\" as referenced by abilities such as Ric Olié's pilot ability."
  },
  {
    "question": "After a Nantex-class starfighter executes its maneuver, if it uses its Pinpoint Tractor Array ship ability to assign a tractor token to itself so that it can rotate its turret arc, and then it barrel rolls itself over a debris field as a result of becoming tractored, giving it a stress token, how does this resolve?",
    "answer": "After a Nantex-class starfighter executes its maneuver, it has the option to add an ability in the queue with the effect of \"gain 1 tractor token to perform a [Rotate] action.\"\n\nWhen this ability resolves, the Nantex-class starfighter pays the cost (\"gain 1 tractor token\") to resolve this effect. The Nantex-class starfighter gains 1 tractor token, then performs the rotate action. Note that it does not resolve the game effect of becoming tractored (which triggers after the first time a ship becomes tractored each round) until after it fully resolves the ability by completing the rotate action.\n\nOnce the ability is fully resolved, the game effect that triggers after a ship becomes tractored is applied to the Nantex-class starfighter (before any other abilities on the queue are resolved), prompting the Nantex-class starfighter's player to move it, if they desire. If they do and this movement takes the Nantex-class starfighter onto a debris cloud, it resolves the effects of moving through or overlapping the debris cloud, including gaining 1 stress token. \n\nFinally, any other abilities on the queue are then resolved in order."
  },
  {
    "question": "Can Snap Shot or Foresight be chosen as a special weapon to be used for a ship's attack during the Engagement Phase?",
    "answer": "Yes. The phrase \"after an enemy ship executes a maneuver, you may perform this attack against it as a bonus attack\" allows the attack to be used as a bonus attack under the specified circumstances, but does not disqualify it from being used during the Engagement Phase."
  }
]
